Guide to the Stewardesses for Women's Rights Oral History Collection OH.012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stewardesses for Women's Rights Oral History Collection
1985-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rapport, Sarah
Parnes, Brenda
OH.012
2.13 Linear Feet in 9 audiocassette tapes in 2 shared cassette boxes and 7 CDs in a shared CD box
7 CDs
9 audiocassettes
98 kilobytes in 2 documents
In 1972, two Eastern Airlines flight attendants, Sandra Jarrell and Jan Fulsom, took Eastern to court on charges of discriminatory weight and grooming regulations. Jarrell and Fulsom decided to band together with other women to fight discrimination and sexism throughout the industry, and they founded Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR) in 1973. Great progress was made in the next few years toward better working conditions, equal treatment with male co-workers, and removing hazardous cargo from passenger flights. By 1976, many SFWR members had become involved in their airlines' respective unions and the SFWR ended due to declining membership and lack of funding. The collection is comprised of two oral history interviews of former SFWR members taken by Sarah Rapport, the recording an event regarding SFWR, a recording of a SFWR commercial, a recording of a slideshow on labor rights for women flight attendants, and a recording of an SFWR meeting.
Historical Note
In 1972, two Eastern Airlines flight attendants, Sandra Jarrell and Jan Fulsom, took Eastern to court on charges of discriminatory weight and grooming regulations. Jarrell and Fulsom decided to band together with other women and fight discrimination and sexism throughout the industry, and the Stewardesses for Women's Rights (SFWR) was founded. In March of 1973, they organized their first national conference held in New York City, which was hosted by Gloria Steinem. In June 1973, the Stern Family Fund granted the SFWR $25,000, which enabled them to open a national office in Rockefeller Center, New York City. Great progress was made in the next few years toward better working conditions, equal treatment with male co-workers, and removing hazardous cargo from passenger flights. Through their involvement with SFWR, many flight attendants became interested and active in their own unions, and thus drifted away from involvement with SFWR. Due to declining membership and lack of funding, SFWR closed its doors in the spring of 1976.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection are arranged in alphabetical order by name or topic. Master cassettes are arranged by an archivist-devised numbering scheme that appears to represent the order that the repository received the materials. Access CDs are arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of two oral history interviews taken by Sarah Rapport, the recording an event regarding Stewardesses for Women's Rights, a recording of a SFWR commercial, a recording of a slideshow on labor rights for women flight attendants, and a recording of an SFWR meeting.
Rapport's interviews are with Kathleen Heenan and Cindy Hounsell. She took them in 1985 while preparing her dissertation on the SFWR. The interviews include discussions of the fight for gender equality in the workplace; airline policies regarding appearance and personal lives; training and the nature of the work; and life as a flight attendant. Additional topics are the activities of the SFWR, the union's internal politics, and the role of feminism for SFWR members.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Sarah Rapport or collected by the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives from former Stewardesses for Women's Rights members, dates unknown. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1987.019, 1987.020, and 1987.021.
Related Archival Materials
Stewardesses for Women's Rights Collection (WAG 061)
Stewardesses for Women's Rights: A Silver Lining, a video by Mary Lennon, is available through the Avery Fisher Center at Bobst Library. (VCA 2623)
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu. with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Sex discrimination against women -- United States.; Sex discrimination in employment--United States; Flight attendants -- United States; Oral history interview; Airlines -- Employees -- Labor unions; Fulsom, Jan; Jarrell, Sandra; Stewardesses for Women's Rights; Eastern Air Lines
- Eve of Change, 1973
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 098, Audiocassette 3)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 1)
- Kathleen Heenan, November 21, 1985
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 098, Audiocassette 1A-B)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 2)
  - Transcript, TW_OH_012_ER_1
- Cindy Hounsell, November 25, 1985
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 098, Audiocassette 2)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 3-4)
- SFWR Commercial, Circa 1974-1975
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 195, Audiocassette 6)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 5)
- SFWR Organizational Meeting (Washington, DC), undated
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 195, Audiocassette 7)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 6)
- SFWR Reunion, April 22, 1987
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 195, Audiocassette 4A-B)
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 123, Cd 7)